<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of repentance. Preached by George Meriton Doctor of Diuinity, and one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinary</title>
            <author>Meriton, George, d. 1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1607</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 66 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07452</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17839</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112669</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847915</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847915</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12983</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07452)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12983)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1248:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of repentance. Preached by George Meriton Doctor of Diuinity, and one of his Maiesties chaplaines in ordinary</title>
                  <author>Meriton, George, d. 1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[48] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[By George Eld] for Thomas Clarke, and are to be sold at the signe of the Angell in Paules Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1607.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf and the last leaf are blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12983:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12983:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON OF REPENTANCE.</p>
            <p>Preached By GEORGE MERITON Doctor of Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and one of his Maieſties Chaplaines <hi>in Ordinary.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Imprinted at London for <hi>Thomas Clarke,</hi> and are to be ſold at the ſigne of the Angell in <hi>Paules</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, 1607.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:12983:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12983:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, the <hi>Lord Sheffeild, Lord Preſident of</hi> Yorke, and Knight of the Honorable Order of the Garter: increaſe of Comforts in this <hi>life, and after death, a</hi> Crowne of Glory.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honourable: <hi>my deſire is to caſt my</hi> Mite, <hi>into the Treaſury of the Church: and for want of Gold, Pearle or Pretious ſtones:</hi> to bring a Rams skinae or twaine, and a little Goats<note place="margin">Exod. 35. 23.</note> haire, <hi>to the building of the Lordes Tabernacle<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I may ſeeme</hi> (<hi>perhaps</hi>) <hi>to paſſe the boundes of modeſty, in crauing your</hi> Honors <hi>protection for ſo ſmal a thing. The</hi> ſmaller <hi>it is, the more needefull to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected. And ſithence</hi> you <hi>vouchſafed not</hi> long ſince, <hi>to heare</hi> part <hi>of it with</hi> patience: <hi>I will</hi> now <hi>preſume vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your</hi> L<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>fauoure for the</hi> whole. <hi>I doe not dedicate it vnto</hi> you, <hi>as doubting of your</hi> Honours care, <hi>in this point of</hi> Repentance, <hi>your</hi> loue <hi>to</hi> Religion: Zeale <hi>to the</hi> Truth: practiſe <hi>of</hi> Piety: <hi>haue made you</hi> Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, <hi>not in</hi> your ſelfe <hi>alone; but alſo</hi> (<hi>as</hi> Samuel<note place="margin">1. Sam. 9. 6.</note> 
               <hi>was</hi>) in the heartes of the people. <hi>Yet giue mee leaue</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 3. 1.</note> (<hi>Ibeſeech you</hi>) to ſtirre vp and warne your pure mind,
<pb facs="tcp:12983:3"/>
               <hi>That as you haue</hi> begun <hi>to cleaue vnto</hi> CHRIST, <hi>with a good purpoſe of heart: So you would</hi> continue <hi>to aoe it</hi> ſtill: <hi>and to do it</hi> more <hi>and</hi> more. <hi>Remember alwayes</hi> (Noble Lord) <hi>that bloud</hi> vnſtayned <hi>before</hi> Men, <hi>is</hi> ſtayned <hi>bloud before</hi> GOD; <hi>if it be not</hi> continually reſtored <hi>by the bloud of</hi> CHRIST. <hi>This Sermon then, I commend vnto</hi> your Honour, <hi>and</hi> it, <hi>to the good bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and holy protection of GOD. Hadleigh in Suffolke, May the</hi> 26. 1607.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours to bee</hi> commanded: GEORGE MERITON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:12983:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Except yee amend your lines, yee all ſhall likewiſe periſh.</p>
                  <bibl>Luk. 13. verſ. 5.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Ther Mens <hi>afflictions,</hi> are our <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions:</hi> and the <hi>puniſhments</hi> which are laid vpon ſome, are, or ſhould be <hi>profitable</hi> vnto vs <hi>all.</hi> The <hi>Dogge,</hi> is beaten in the preſence of a <hi>Lyon;</hi> that by the ſtripes, and cries of a <hi>Dogge,</hi> a <hi>Lyon</hi> might bee tamed; The <hi>Thunder bolt,</hi> falleth, and burneth, but in a <hi>narrow</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud. verſ. 7.</note> 
               <hi>compaſſe,</hi> yet is it terrible to a <hi>great number,</hi> round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout: ſo the <hi>calamities of a few,</hi> are ſet forth for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples vnto <hi>the reſt,</hi> to worke amendment in them. This true vſe of iudgements, did not many of the Iewiſh people make: <hi>Pilate</hi> had <hi>deſtroyed ſome, and mingled their blood,</hi> with their ſacrifices: <hi>The Towre of Siloam fell downe vpon others, and bereaued them of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 4.</note> 
               <hi>their liues.</hi> Thoſe who eſcaped theſe puniſhments, (as the Nature of man is) fauouring them ſelues too much: beeing <hi>wiſe</hi> abroad, and <hi>fooles</hi> at home (as the Poet ſpeaketh:) hauing their eyes in their <hi>purſes,</hi> when they ſhould behold their owne deformities, like <hi>Lamia</hi> in the Fable, and <hi>ſtaring in their heades,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12983:4"/>
to gaze vpon the ſinnes of others, with the proud Phareſie in the Goſpell: concluded from hence, like badde Logitians from weake and ſlender premiſes: that, <hi>Therefore they were more righteous and holy then their fellowes.</hi> Our Sauiour CHRIST, to croſſe this vaine ſuppoſall, anſwereth them heere Laconically: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: Nay: And leaſt that beeing ouer-blinded in themſelues, they ſhould <hi>all</hi> fall into the ditch: to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent their ruine, hee denounceth out a threatning, that, <hi>Vnleſſe they amended, they ſhould</hi> all <hi>likewiſe periſh.</hi> Threatnings they are forcible meanes, to draw ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners vnto GOD: For although <hi>good</hi> promiſes, are alurements vnto <hi>good</hi> men: yet ſuch (for the moſt part) is the corruption of our heartes, as that wee are more mooued with <hi>feare,</hi> then with <hi>loue;</hi> more with the rodde of <hi>Aaron,</hi> then with heauenly <hi>Manna:</hi> more with ſeuere <hi>threatnings,</hi> then with friendly <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſings: Injuries</hi> do worke a deeper griefe in vs, then <hi>benefits</hi> do affect vs with delight: <hi>Sickneſse</hi> doth more weary vs, then <hi>health</hi> doth refreſh vs: and wee are wont to eſteeme rightly of <hi>proſperity;</hi> by the harmes of <hi>aduerſity.</hi> For this cauſe therfore are theſe miſdee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Iews, fore-told, that vnleſſe they ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded their liues, their deſtruction was at hand. CHRIST <hi>laun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth</hi> them, for to <hi>heale</hi> them: hee <hi>threatneth</hi> them; for to <hi>draw</hi> them: hee <hi>denounceth</hi> iudgements againſt them, for to <hi>ſaue</hi> them: his wordes are like the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes of <hi>Ionathan,</hi> which were ſhot after <hi>Dauid,</hi> not<note place="margin">1. Sam. 20.</note> to <hi>wound</hi> him, but to giue him <hi>warning.</hi> In <hi>olde times,</hi> thus was GOD accuſtomed to reclaime his
<pb facs="tcp:12983:4"/>
people: The writinges of the Prophets are euen ſtuffed with woes. <hi>Take a booke</hi> ſaith GOD vnto<note place="margin">Ier: 36. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Ieremy, and write therein all the euill, that I determine to doe vnto the houſe of</hi> Iudah, <hi>that they may returnee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man from his euill way:</hi> and in the ſame Chapter it is recorded, that <hi>when they heard the wordes of the booke they were amazed.</hi> The like courſe hath GOD vſed in <hi>latter times. Iohns</hi> manner of preaching, was as rough, as himſelfe. <hi>Now is the Axe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>laid vnto the rootes of the trees, and euery tree that brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 3. 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>not forth good fruit, ſhall bee hewen downe, and caſt into the fire:</hi> What followed herevpon? Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, <hi>all</hi> Iudea, <hi>and the region about</hi> Iordaine <hi>were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized of him, confeſſing their ſinnes.</hi> CHRIST alſo in <hi>this place</hi> threatneth the Iewes, and in them euerie one of vs: for that which ſtoode good againſt them, ſtandeth ſtill in force againſt vs: <hi>Except we amendour liues, we ſhall</hi> all <hi>likewiſe periſh.</hi> How this wrought, to the conuerſion of theſe Iewes, it is not mentioned in the Scripture; how farre it will preuaile, for the bettering of vs, I am not able to coniecture. This am I ſure of, that in former times, threatnings haue preuailed: and I beſeech our GOD to make them profitable now. The partes of my Text are theſe foure. Firſt, there is a duty required (<hi>Amendment of life</hi>) Secondly the neceſſity thereof inforced (<hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſse</hi>) Thirdly the time preſcribed (<hi>Amend</hi>) not haue amended and fallen againe, not will amend, I know not when; but vnleſſe you (<hi>Amend</hi>) doe it ſpeedily, and continually without delaye or interruption.
<pb facs="tcp:12983:5"/>
ſorrow for ſin, without hope of grace: where there is <hi>knowledge</hi> of guiltineſſe, without <hi>amendment</hi> of life: where there is a <hi>killing</hi> of the old ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; without a <hi>quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of the newe: where there is the ſentence of <hi>death</hi> in the Soule, &amp; not of <hi>life</hi> in the Sauiour. Though we ſhould recount vnto GOD, all our ſinnes ouer, &amp; ouer againe; euen in the bitternes of our ſoules;<note place="margin">M. ch. 1. 8</note> though we lament with Dragons, and mourne like Oſtriges, yet had we but that part of this grace, which euen the wicked and reprobates haue; <hi>Cain, Saul, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 17</note> were greatly grieued for theyr ſinnes, <hi>Eſau</hi> lift vp his voice, and howled out, <hi>yet found hee no</hi> place to repentance, <hi>though hee ſought a bleſsing with teares.</hi> What was the cauſe of this? (<hi>my beloued</hi>) but that there was in him <hi>penance</hi> without deſire of <hi>repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance; griefe</hi> without <hi>faith,</hi> a <hi>ſorrow</hi> without <hi>conuerſion:</hi> whereas <hi>ſorrow, faith,</hi> and <hi>new obedience,</hi> they ſhould go together. The <hi>firſt,</hi> driueth to the ſecond; <hi>ſorrow,</hi> to <hi>faith:</hi> The <hi>ſecond</hi> to the <hi>third:</hi> fayth, to <hi>conuerſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Sorrow</hi> without <hi>faith</hi> is hopeleſſe; <hi>faith</hi> without <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion,</hi> is fruitleſſe; the one <hi>killing,</hi> the other <hi>dead,</hi> all muſt concurre in true repentance. As it muſt haue the <hi>knowledge</hi> of ſinne in the <hi>ſoule,</hi> riſing from the Law of GOD; and a ſorrow for ſinne in the heart, proceeding from the <hi>feare</hi> of puniſhment goe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it: ſo muſt it ſpring from faith, and by faith bee finiſhed: from the faith of ſcience, wherby wee giue credance vnto the Goſpell muſt it ſpring: and by the faith of <hi>confidence,,</hi> by which the heart is conuerted vnto GOD, is it fully perfected.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12983:5"/>
            <p>There is no part of Chriſtian religion of that maine importance, wherein men doe more voluntarily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue themſelues: then commonly they doe in this duty of Repentance. In conſideration whereof it will not be amiſſe, to deliuer vnto you certaine infallible fignes, and vnſeparable frutes; whereby we may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure our ſelues that wee haue repented. S. <hi>Paul</hi> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſeuen fruites which (in ſome meaſure) alwaies follow, where true amendment goeth before. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>your godly ſorrowes what care</hi> (1) <hi>it hath</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 7. 11</note> 
               <hi>wrought in you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea what clearing</hi> (2) <hi>of your ſelues: yea what indignation</hi> (3): <hi>yea what feare</hi> (4). <hi>yea how great deſire</hi> (5)<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>yea what Zeale</hi> (6): <hi>yea what puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (7)? Thoſe then who are true conuertes, who doe vnfaynedly amend their liues: they are not ſlug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſh or ſecure in ſinne, but <hi>Carefull</hi> to redreſſe what is amiſſe: not hiders, or excuſers of cuill: but Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors; and by humble ſupplication <hi>Clearing</hi> theyr offences: They are not contented to dwell in wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe: but vexed in ſoule and full of <hi>Indignation</hi> againſt them-ſelues for their ſins committed, they ſtand in awe, and are <hi>affraid</hi> of GODS iudgments. They <hi>Deſire</hi> his fauour, as the Hart deſireth the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Brookes: they labour by religious <hi>Zeale,</hi> to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue their liues, to GOD and good Men: and they are ſo farre from fauoring of their faults; as that they ſeuerely <hi>puniſh</hi> them vpon them-ſelues. Theſe bee good Conuerts indeede. But thoſe who haue not this <hi>care</hi> to keepe the Law of GOD. Who vſe not the meanes to <hi>cleare</hi> the ſcore: who be not <hi>angry</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12983:6"/>
with them-ſelues for their ſinnes: who <hi>feare</hi> not GODS iudgements, who <hi>deſire</hi> not his mercie: who contend not to go before others in <hi>Zeale,</hi> and honeſty of life: who <hi>reuenge</hi> not their ſinnes vppon them-ſelues: <hi>irridentes ſunt, non paenitentes</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi>) they are proud mockers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> not true repenters. Muſt then amendment of life, yeelde ſuch worthy fruites? Is <hi>Care?</hi> Is <hi>Clearing?</hi> Is <hi>Indignation?</hi> Is <hi>Feare?</hi> Is <hi>Deſire?</hi> Is <hi>Zeale?</hi> Is <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> required heere-vnto? O then (<hi>My beloued</hi>) to repent, can bee no light matter, nor trifling labour; which a man may haue at command, or performe when hee liſt. No, noe: As ſixe dayes went before the <hi>creation</hi> of Man-kind: ſo muſt wee thinke of our <hi>Recreation;</hi> not as if wee were then <hi>conuerted,</hi> when as Euening, and Morning, make the ſecond, or third or fourth day: it is a ſixt dayes worke: that is, much toyle and trauaile belongs vnto it. Sinne cannot be caſt off as an vpper garment. The heartes of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners muſt ſuffer an Earth-quake with-in them, and tremble, and rende: There muſt bee <hi>mortifying,</hi> and <hi>crucifying;</hi> and <hi>ſacrificing,</hi> both of Bodyes and Soules. Strange wordes! (<hi>Mortifiyng, Crucifying, Sacrifyeing</hi>) arguing as ſtrange actions. That muſt <hi>torment</hi> vs at the <hi>Heart,</hi> which <hi>delighted</hi> vs in our <hi>Bodies:</hi> that muſt bee <hi>ſower</hi> to our <hi>Soules,</hi> which was ſweete in our <hi>Liues:</hi> wee muſt change our <hi>Vices</hi> into as manye <hi>Vertues:</hi> and ſo turne vnto our GOD, as if wee neuer more would returne vnto ſinne.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12983:6"/>
            <p>Many are there (ſaith <hi>Fulgentius</hi>) which are ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for their ſinnes, yet leaue not their ſinning<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but theſe take not awaye their ſinnes by ſorrowing; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they leaue not ſinning after ſorrowing. For as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>nihil proſunt lamenta vbi replicantur peccata: Mourning is in vaine, if wee ſinne againe.</hi> But more (alas) are there, which ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or neuer, are ſorrie for theyr ſinnes at all: Which will not learne to drinke Gall with CHRIST, which cannot abide a bitter Soule, nay in ſteed of ſorrowing for ſins, they glory in them; they ſay vnto them, as GOD ſaid vnto his Creatures: <hi>increaſe &amp; multiplie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> proclayming with a Trumpet, their own reprobation. O let vs remember, that the <hi>hearts of</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 20.</note> 
               <hi>fooliſh ſinners, are like broken veſſells</hi> which cannot be mended, till they muſt firſt bee melted: That (as <hi>Beda</hi> ſayth) we muſt plowe vp our groundes, before wee can ridde them from thornes. That (as Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſpeaketh) great ſinnes, craues great wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, great lamentation. If <hi>Naman</hi> will bee clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from his leproſie, hee muſt waſh him-ſelfe ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen times in the water: and if wee will purge vs from the filthineſſe of our ſinne, wee muſt rench our ſelues often with teares, wee muſt vnder-goe the <hi>Agonie</hi> of Repentance: mingle our Drinke with <hi>weeping,</hi> water our Couches with <hi>Teares:</hi> yea the very <hi>bloud</hi> (as it were) of our ſoules muſt guſh out of our eyes: we muſt be grieued, that wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not alwayes be grieued.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12983:7"/>
            <p>When CHRIST conſidered the ſinnes of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 13. 34</note> he wept ouer it: O <hi>Ieruſalem, Ieruſalem &amp;c.</hi> When <hi>Dauid</hi> heard that his Sonne was ſlaine in his ſinne, he<note place="margin">2, Sam. 18.</note> lamented for him: <hi>O</hi> Abſolon <hi>my ſonne,</hi> Abſolon <hi>my ſonne; my ſonne.</hi> Haue theſe wept for the ſinnes of others? much more ought wee then to mourne for our owne tranſgreſſions. <hi>Michah</hi> followed the ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers; crying becauſe they had ſtolne away his Idols; and the queſtion beeing moued, why he cryed ſo pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly?<note place="margin">Iudges. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Why</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>yee haue carried my gods away, and aske yee me why I crie?</hi> Did this Idolatrous wretch thinke it cauſe ſufficient to lament for the loſſe of his falſe gods, which his owne handes had made? Iudge you then (<hi>Beloued</hi>) how we ſhould be grieued for our ſinnes, which depriue vs of the true GOD whoſe handes haue framed Heauen and Earth. Wil examples moue vs to the performance of this duty? Looke vpon repenting <hi>Dauid,</hi> and behold there are aſhes vpon his head, and ſack-cloth vpon his backe: he did not braue it in atire, nor lay ſtreaking vpon his bed, with a bare (<hi>Lord helpe mee</hi>) in his mouth. Looke vpon the repenting <hi>Nineuites;</hi> and behold King, and people, are ſtrangely humbled. Men and beaſts, faſt and drinke water; they ſat not bealching at their bordes, ſaying (<hi>Pardon Sir</hi>) &amp; ſo poſt it ouer. Looke vpon repenting <hi>Magdalen.</hi> and behold (ſaith <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>) <hi>quot habuit in ſe oblect amenta, tet de ſe fecit hollo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſta:</hi> ſo many <hi>pleaſures</hi> as ſhee found in her ſelfe, ſo many <hi>ſacrifices</hi> ſhee made of her ſelfe. Shee had abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed her eyes to wanton lookes; and therefore nowe
<pb facs="tcp:12983:7"/>
ſhe cauſed them to <hi>flow-ouer with teares:</hi> ſhee had made her <hi>lips</hi> the weapons of laſciuiouſnes and gates of vanitie, and therefore now ſhee cauſed them to <hi>kiſse her Saniour:</hi> her <hi>hayre</hi> once ſet out and frizeled after the neweſt faſhion, doth ſhee now make ſerue in ſteed of a <hi>napkin;</hi> her precious <hi>ointment,</hi> that was her wonted perfume, ſhe now powred vpon CHRISTS <hi>feete,</hi> which her <hi>eyes</hi> had <hi>watered,</hi> her <hi>hayre</hi> had <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped,</hi> her <hi>mouth</hi> had <hi>kiſſed.</hi> The <hi>Philiſtins</hi> being pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gued with Emrodes, <hi>offered Emrodes vnto the Arke.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Sam. 6.</note> The <hi>Iſralites</hi> being ſtong with Serpents, <hi>erected a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent in the wildernes, ſerpens momordit, ſerpens curauit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 21.</note> a Serpent did bite, &amp; a ſerpent did heale. Thoſe that gaue their Iewels to the making of a Calfe, did <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ex. 35.</note> 
               <hi>beſtow them vpon the Lords Tabernacle.</hi> And this was <hi>Maries</hi> practiſe: ſo many <hi>ſinnes,</hi> ſo many <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices:</hi> ſuch <hi>ſinnes</hi> ſuch <hi>ſacrifices:</hi> her <hi>eyes,</hi> her <hi>lippes,</hi> her <hi>hayre,</hi> her <hi>ointment,</hi> all the <hi>inſtruments</hi> of her <hi>death</hi> were turned (at her conuerſion) into the <hi>means</hi> of <hi>life.</hi> Notable examples to teach <hi>all</hi> their duties. Haue you delighted in pride of attire? put on ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth: haue you offended in ſurfetting, &amp; drankennes? faſt and drinke water: hath your mirth beene immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate? weepe; ſtrangle that ſinne with the ſtreame of teares: haue you robbed or wronged your bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren? make reſtitution: <hi>no reſtitution, no attonement.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 6. 7.</note> Nay further reuenge that ſinne vpon your ſelues; by giuing ſome-what of your own: haue you beene vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane, fleſhly liuers? chaſtiſe your bodies with <hi>Paul: demete aliquid de hordeo,</hi> as it is in the Poet, keepe<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9. 27.</note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12983:8"/>
before his couenant: as <hi>Amend:</hi> and <hi>Enter:</hi> but <hi>Niſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> vnleſſe you amend, <hi>Regnum amittitur,</hi> the Kingdome is loſt, ye ſhall ſurely periſh: Repentance is as <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary a condition</hi> to life, as a Shippe is needefull to him that will ſayle ouer the Sea: or as a medicine is neceſſary (ſaith <hi>S. Ambroſe</hi>) vnto a wounded body. Neither is it neceſſary to <hi>ſome:</hi> but to <hi>all. All ſhall pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, vnleſſe there be amendment.</hi> The whole race of <hi>Adam</hi> ſtand bound to this ſtrict <hi>condition.</hi> Not <hi>Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes:</hi> Not <hi>Abraham<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Not <hi>Dauid:</hi> not the <hi>Patriarches</hi> not the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> of CHRIST: Not <hi>any</hi> who may challenge vnto them-ſelues (eyther by Birth or brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging vp) the greateſt prerogatiues in the world, can plead exemption from this <hi>Condition.</hi> Haſt thou fayled in thy <hi>faith,</hi> and <hi>repented?</hi> behold GODS mercy towards <hi>repenting</hi> Peter: Haſt thou robbed thy Neighbour and <hi>repented?</hi> behold GODS mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to the <hi>repenting Theefe:</hi> Haſt thou couetouſly gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and <hi>repented?</hi> behold GODS mercy to <hi>repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zachy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored.</note> Zachie. Haſt thou burned in <hi>vncleane luſt,</hi> and <hi>repented?</hi> behold GODS mercy to <hi>repenting</hi> Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalen. Haſt thou <hi>committed Adultery,</hi> and <hi>repented?</hi> behold GODS mercy to <hi>repenting</hi> Dauid. But haſt thou done <hi>theſe</hi> and <hi>many more:</hi> and not <hi>repented:</hi> take heede to thy ſelfe: if the <hi>condition</hi> bee ſtill broken: thou ſhalt ſurely be <hi>damned.</hi> GOD accepteth of no mans perſon: he feareth no mans power, hee is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued by no policie; he is corrupted with no money, he is allured by no flatterie. Who would not haue thought, but that the Phariſies ſhould haue beene
<pb facs="tcp:12983:8"/>
ſaued, which made a ſhewe of a preciſe life: or that <hi>Eſau</hi> ſhould not haue beene reſpected, who lift vp his voice and wept bitterly. Or that <hi>Ahab</hi> had not bin<note place="margin">Heb. 12.</note> in good caſe who humbled him-ſelfe exceedingly: Or that <hi>Herod</hi> ſhould not haue gon to Heauen: who<note place="margin">2. King. 21</note> heard <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> gladly. But <hi>wo</hi> vnto the <hi>Phareſies</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mar. 6. 20.</note> ſaid CHRIST. <hi>Eſau</hi> did GOD <hi>hate: Achab</hi> was a<note place="margin">Luk. 11. 42</note> counterfeit, <hi>Herod</hi> was a cruell Tyrant. Will not a<note place="margin">Mal. 1. 3.</note> ſeeming preciſe life, out-ward humility, crying for<note place="margin">2 Kin. 21.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Luk. 3. 19. 20.</note> a bleſſing, hearing of GODS word with ſome gladneſſe ſerue our turnes? No verily: I may ſay of this <hi>condition,</hi> as <hi>S. Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of Charity. <hi>Though</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor 13<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> 
               <hi>wee ſpake with the tongues of men and Angells: though we had the gift of Propheſiyng, and knew all ſecrets: though we had faith to remoue mountaines: though we ſhould feed the poore with all our goods<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though we ſhould giue our bodies to be burned;</hi> and want <hi>Repentance:</hi> all would be nothing worth: but like the Golden Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Caligula,</hi> which might pleaſe the ſight of his Gheſts (ſaith <hi>Plutarch</hi>) but not ſlake their hunger: or like the gold on the out-ſide of the Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple, which (as <hi>Origen</hi> writeth) was neuer ſanctified: <hi>Say</hi> what wee can: <hi>beleeue</hi> what wee can, <hi>doe</hi> what wee can: <hi>ſuffer</hi> what wee can: <hi>vnleſſe we repent</hi> wee ſhall ſurely pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. As CHRIST IESVS is a Lambe full of mercy<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.</note> &amp; meekneſſe: ſo is he a <hi>Lyon,</hi> full of wrath &amp; fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.<note place="margin">Apo. 5.</note> Vnto the <hi>repenting</hi> perſon he giueth a <hi>ſoft heart, for his mercy indureth for euer:</hi> he ſendeth <hi>the comfort</hi> of his <hi>ſpirit: for his mercy indureth for euer:</hi> hee giueth <hi>peace of conſcience: for his mercy indureth for euer:</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:12983:9"/>
beſtoweth on them <hi>the ioyes of Heauen; for his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy indureth for euer.</hi> But as for the <hi>impenitent:</hi> hee giueth them ouer vnto <hi>hardneſſe</hi> of heart: <hi>for his iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice indureth for euer.</hi> Hee leaueth them, in a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probate ſenſe, for his iuſtice indureth for euer.</hi> Hee ſendeth into them the horror <hi>of Conſcience, for his iuſtice indureth for euer.</hi> And cafteth them at laſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>torments of Hell: for his iuſtice indureth for</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jud. 6.</note> 
               <hi>euer.</hi> Did not GOD ſpare his Angells, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued<note place="margin">Gen. 7.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Num. 14.</note> them in Chaynes vnder darkeneſſe? did hee not ſpare the olde World, but drowned it with a flood? did hee not ſpare his owne people, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed them in the Wilderneſſe? And will hee ſpare vs without our conuerſion? Is there nowe an other waye to Heauen? or a newe tricke to eſcape danger? Let no Man flatter him-ſelfe there is no Atheiſt, no Drunken ſwil-tubbe, no Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous wreatch, no doting Dreamer, who deſpiſeth gouernment, and ſpeaketh euill of thoſe that are in Authoritie: no Swearer, no For-ſwearer: no Theefe, no Adulterer. In one word no kind of ſinner, without <hi>Repentance</hi> ſhall eſcape GODS vengeance. CHRIST IESVS hath ſpoken it: the <hi>Life</hi> that fayleth not: the <hi>Way</hi> that miſleadeth not: the <hi>trueth</hi> that deceiueth not. <hi>Vnleſſe yee amend your liues, yee ſhall</hi> all <hi>likewiſe periſh.</hi> Thus much of the neceſſity of this duty,</p>
            <p n="3">3. The time is preſcribed. <hi>Amend</hi> inſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In omnibus obligationibus, in quibus dies non poni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, preſente die debetur:</hi> In all Obligations (ſayth
<pb facs="tcp:12983:9"/>
the Lawyer) where no time is ſpecified the Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is preſently to bee performed. Vppon this Theame the Holy-Men of GOD ſpent many of their Sermons: Looke into <hi>Eſay, Ieremy</hi> and the reſt, and you ſhall finde, that they euer beate vppon the preſent time: <hi>Now turne vnto the Lord. Now,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Efa. 55.</note> 
               <hi>whilest it is called to day; to day if you will heare his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 35.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Heb. 3.</note> 
               <hi>voice, this is the acceptable time &amp;c.</hi> What were<note place="margin">Pſal. 95.</note> they ſo barren headed; as that penurie conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<note place="margin">Heb. 4.</note> them to harpe alwayes vpon the ſame ſtring? GOD forbid wee ſhould thinke ſo. But iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty did then abound (as now it doth) and procraſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, was euer dangerous: and therefore they iudged no Doctrine ſo fit, as oftentimes to vrge re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance without all delay. GOD will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte vs, to giue the <hi>prime</hi> dayes vnto the Deuill: and the <hi>Dogge</hi> dayes to him: to poure out our <hi>wine</hi> to the world, and ſerue him with our <hi>dregges. Amend</hi> (ſaith my text) heere is no time ſpeciall annexed? and therefore is our payment preſently required. And as we muſt <hi>amend,</hi> without <hi>deferring<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> ſo muſt wee <hi>continue</hi> without <hi>back-ſliding.</hi> Wee may not repent by quames and ſtartes, but go through ſtitch. <hi>Fatte</hi> promiſings may not haue <hi>leane</hi> performances. It is a principle in the Ciuill Law. <hi>Nihil praeſumitur fuiſſe actum, dum aliquid ſupereſt ad agendum.</hi> To be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin a thing is pleaſant, and for varieties ſake many will do ſo much, but the priſe and praiſe is at the end. Some in the world reſemble Snayles, which puſh out a long payre of hornes, but beeing touched neuer ſo
<pb facs="tcp:12983:10"/>
little, they drawe them in againe. Such a one was<note place="margin">2. Chr. 15.</note> 
               <hi>Aſa,</hi> carefull to doe good, till the goute did take him;<note place="margin">1. Sam. 14. 27.</note> Others are like <hi>Ionathan,</hi> who will follow the chaſe hard, till they come where hony is. But <hi>true repentance</hi> may not be by leaſe, or after the manner of <hi>Bethulia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 7. 30.</note> a compoſition for fiue dayes: wee may not ſay one day <hi>Gloriapatri,</hi> the ſecond <hi>&amp; filio,</hi> the third <hi>&amp; ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuo ſancto:</hi> and after that come to <hi>ſicut erat in principio;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 2. 32. 33.</note> this were <hi>Nabuchadnezers</hi> image, the head of braſſe the breaſt of baſer mettall, and ſo neerer the ende<note place="margin">Luk. 18.</note> worſe and worſe ſtill. But we muſt follow <hi>repentance</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 32.</note> as the widdow did her ſute, keepe our hold as <hi>Iacob</hi> did in wreſtling. <hi>Amend</hi> to day, <hi>amend</hi> to morrow<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> runne on, not for a time, but euen our whole time: <hi>actu continuo</hi> with a continued act, <hi>Moderately</hi> at the firſt; <hi>conſtantly</hi> in the middeſt; <hi>cheerefully</hi> to the end. All the trees in GODS Orchard muſt bee <hi>Palmes</hi> and <hi>Cedars: Palmes,</hi> which bring forth fruit betimes; <hi>Cedars,</hi> whoſe fruites laſteth very long.</p>
            <p>Conſider well, the manifold dangers which fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes the want eyther of <hi>ſpeed</hi> or of <hi>continuance.</hi> Firſt our liues, of all things are moſt vncertaine. <hi>Short are</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 13.</note> 
               <hi>the dayes of man</hi> ſaith <hi>Iob,</hi> who alſo amonſt the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers is but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a man of a day old. <hi>Salomon</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccle. 2.</note> ſurueying mans life calleth it <hi>Vaine:</hi> and then think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing not that word ſufficient, correcteth himſelfe and calleth it <hi>vanity:</hi> but <hi>Dauid</hi> goeth yet further, and<note place="margin">Pſal. 6 2.</note> tells vs. That man <hi>is lighter then vanity too.</hi> Euen as<note place="margin">Pſal. 90. 9.</note> a <hi>thought</hi> in the braine, wherof there may be no few<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then ten thouſand in one day. What anſwer was
<pb facs="tcp:12983:10"/>
made vnto him that promiſed eaſe vnto his ſoule ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny yeares? <hi>thou foole this night ſhall thy ſoule be taken</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 11. 19 20.</note> 
               <hi>from thee.</hi> Young men (ſaith <hi>Seneca</hi>) haue death behind them: olde men haue death before them: and all men haue death not farre from them. Mee thinkes the Lord threatneth an vtter ruine vnto all the World: The Earth not long ſince hath trembled: the Lightes of Heauen haue beene often darkened. Rebellions haue beene raiſed. Treaſons haue beene practiſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Plagues haue beene diſperſed, Windes haue bluſtered: Waters haue raged, and what wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth there now, but fire for vs, from Heauen to bee conſumed? And is it nowe time to buye, to ſell, to eate, to drinke, to liue ſecurely in ſinne, as they did in the dayes of <hi>Noah,</hi> and thinke of nothing elſe? Is it nowe time to ſay vnto GOD as the Niggard doth<note place="margin">Prou. 3.</note> vnto his neighbour, <hi>Cras reuertere, come againe to morrow?</hi> or as that drowſie ſluggard doth; <hi>yet a</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prou. 6. 10.</note> 
               <hi>little ſleepe, yet a little ſlumber, yet a little folding of the handes?</hi> The fooliſh Virgins ſuppoſed that the Brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome would not come like an Owle or Ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te in the night: there is time enough (ſaide they:) what needes all this haſt? but poore fooles they were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded. O (<hi>My beloued</hi>) many <hi>thouſands</hi> are nowe, no doubt in hell, who <hi>purpoſed in time</hi> to haue tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from their ſinnes, but being <hi>preuented</hi> by death are for euer condemned. Let therefore the <hi>vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainety</hi> and <hi>ſhortneſſe</hi> of our liues, teach vs to watch <hi>becauſe we know not the houre, to do good whilſt we haue</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 6.</note> 
               <hi>time; to make haſt into the promiſed reſt,</hi> and alwayes<note place="margin">Heb. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note>
               <pb facs="tcp:12983:11"/>
let vs eſteeme it, as an imminent danger, to line in that eſtate, wherein wee would bee loath that death ſhould finde vs.</p>
            <p>Secondly badde cuſtomes are dangerous, and<note place="margin">Iob. 20. 11</note> greatly to bee feared: <hi>Hee that from his youth hath liued wickedly, in his old age ſhall haue ſinne in his bones. Can the Black-moore change his skinne, or the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 13. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Leopard his ſpottes? no more may hee doe good</hi> (ſayth GOD) <hi>who is accuſtomed vnto euill.</hi> It is a true ſpeech vſed amongſt Phyſitions, <hi>Custome is another Nature.</hi> A Child brought vp in cloſſe priſon, can there ſport and play: when hee that lately ſaw light, and had his liberty: can do little elſe but bewayle his Captiuity: The Iſralites beeing long in bondage,<note place="margin">Luk. 13.</note> were loath to depart; the Woman which had an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie eighteene yeares, called not vpon CHRIST<note place="margin">Luk. 19.</note> as the Leapers did. Sinnes are not like Diſſeaſes in the body. <hi>The older the ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r: ſed conſuetudine plus quam ciues ſtudio plus quam hoſtes</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustine</hi>) <hi>the older the ſweeter,</hi> and yet the more <hi>toothſome,</hi> the more <hi>troubleſome:</hi> for Cuſtome not reſiſted becommeth a Neceſſity. Olde <hi>Sinners</hi> are compared to <hi>Lazarus</hi> in his graue. Firſt, they ſtinke: they are corrupt, and become abhomma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble<note place="margin">Pſ. 14. 1. 3.</note> as the Pſalmiſt ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they haue a greate ſtone of Cuſtome rowled vpon them, which can hardly be remoued:<note place="margin">Ioh. 11. 43.</note> CHRIST muſt grone and crye aloud, before <hi>Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> can bee raiſed.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly their ſeete and handes, are bound, they
<pb facs="tcp:12983:11"/>
cannot imploie them to any good action. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> their faces are couered, hauing by the darkeneſſe of their ſinnes, loſt the ſight of GOD. Againe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>ſinnes,</hi> are by the Prophet compared vnto Chaynes: where one lincke, one ſinne doth draw on another. Firſt commeth ſecret <hi>ſuggeſtion,</hi> after ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion, <hi>Cogitation:</hi> after cogitation, <hi>Affection:</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter affection <hi>Delight:</hi> after delight, <hi>Conſent:</hi> after conſent an <hi>Act:</hi> then many actes make a <hi>Cuſtome:</hi> Cuſtome bringeth <hi>Deſpayre:</hi> deſpaire a <hi>Defence</hi> of ſinne: defenſe a <hi>Boaſting</hi> in it: and this is the next ſteppe to <hi>condemnation.</hi> Here is the Chaine of ſinn: wherein euerie lincke is more heauye then an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: the former, are the eaſier: the latter, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes the harder to bee ſhaken off. <hi>Peter</hi> at the <hi>firſt</hi> did but denye CHRIST, <hi>afterwardes</hi> hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed him with an oath: at <hi>last</hi> hee did <hi>curſe</hi> and <hi>ſwcare,</hi> and <hi>for-ſwore</hi> him-ſelfe. The Diſciples of<note place="margin">Mat. 26.</note> CHRIST could not caſte out a Foule Spirit, that had remayned in one from his child-hood. Hee that hath had long poſſeſſion, will plead preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">Mar. 9.</note> A Language (ſaith <hi>Baſsill</hi>) firſt learned; is not ſoone forgotten, and a cuſtome long retayned, is not quickly changed. It is therefore very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, not to examine or trie our ſelues before wee bee indged: not to vſe phiſicke before wee bee deadly ſicke: not to repent before wee can ſinne no more.</p>
            <p>It wil be too late, to come to the kaye when the ſhip is launched: too late, to tranſplant trees, when they
<pb facs="tcp:12983:12"/>
be growne in yeares: too late to apply a medicine, where the diſeaſe is deſperate: too late to reſiſt ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, when they haue gotten, and fortefyed the hold: too late to ſeaſon fleſh, when it crawleth with wormes: or to mend a houſe when it is on fire. So ſtandeth the caſe with him that hath lined long in ſinne: what is there no hope of Saluation for him? <hi>Non dico ſaluabitur, non dico damnabitur</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) I will not ſay, he ſhall be ſaued, I will not ſay, he ſhall be damned. The <hi>Theefe</hi> was receined in the <hi>end</hi> of his dayes. Where vpon <hi>Origen</hi> writeth thus. There is no man which hath cauſe to diſpayre of pardon: ſeeing CHRIST ſaid vnto the Theefe, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men dico tibi, &amp;c. verily this day ſhalt Thou bee with me in Paradiſe:</hi> and yet may we not too much preſume of pardon, becauſe CHRIST ſayde not. <hi>Amen dico vobis, &amp;c verily this day ſhall You bee with mee in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe.</hi> Wherefore let vs remember before wee ſin; that CHRIST pardoned not the <hi>multitude;</hi> and thereby feare his iuſtice. And <hi>after we haue ſinned,</hi> let vs remember that CHRIST pardoned the <hi>theefe;</hi> and thereby hope for mercy. <hi>Et ſi paenitentia eſt ſera, tamen indulgentia non eſt fera,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lombard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> GODS mercy is aboue our miſery: and an euening ſacrifice is accepted by him, And yet on the other ſide: wee neuer read, that CHRIST cured one blind man of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; that he healed the ſame Leapers <hi>diuerſe</hi> times: that hee raiſed <hi>Lazarus</hi> twice. <hi>Antiochus</hi> prayed for mercy at the ende of his life and was not heard.<note place="margin">2. Macha. 6</note> Hee that ſayeth, at what time ſoeuer a ſinner doth
<pb facs="tcp:12983:12"/>
repent, I will put away his wickedneſſe: ſaith alſo,<note place="margin">Eze. 33.</note> it is good for a man to beare the yoak from his youth:<note place="margin">Lam. 3. 27.</note> for olde age is like to flint, you may breake it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you can ſoften it: and therefore the wiſeman ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſeth, to bow <hi>downe the neck of thy ſonne whileſt hee is</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccl. 10. 12</note> 
               <hi>young;</hi> to beate ſinne on the ſides, to <hi>nippe it</hi> on the head while it is a child: for it will elſe grow ſtubborn, and get the Maſtery. In youth, ſinnes are few and fec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; but by continuance they grow to be as ſtrong as Gyants, and increaſe into mighty Armies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Beſides they are a burden; heauier then the whole earth. They made wicked Angells to fall like thunder-bolts<note place="margin">Iud. verſ. 6.</note> from the Higheſt Heauen, into the loweſt Hell: they cauſed GOD to complaine. <hi>Behold I am preſſed vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amo. 2. 13</note> 
               <hi>you, as a Cart is preſſed that is full of ſheaues.</hi> The creatures grone vnder this burthen; beeing by mans ſinne, ſubiect to vanity, and corruption; and ſhall<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 22.</note> crooked age be able to ſuſtaine it? A thouſand to one wee ſhall bee conſtrayned to crie out with <hi>Cain. My</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 13.</note> 
               <hi>ſinne is heauier then I am able for to beare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly we muſt remember, that the longer wee <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> continue in ſinne, the farther and greater ſpace, we runne from our GOD. <hi>Your Iniquities</hi> (ſaith GOD) <hi>makes a Separation betwixt mee and you.</hi> And is there<note place="margin">Eſa. 59. 2.</note> any likelyhood, that he who hath beene running from his GOD, forty, threeſcore, perhappes foureſcore yeares together, who with the prodigall, is runne in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a farre Countrey: can returne againe, in the ſpace of ſixe dayes? ſixe houres? ſixe minutes? For it may be his ſicknes, (vnto the time whereof
<pb facs="tcp:12983:13"/>
hee deferreth his conuerſion) will not be ſixe daies, ſixe houres, ſixe minutes long: and how is it poſſible then to returne vnto GOD? Say that the forcea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble working of the holy ſpirit (like a great gale of wind) bee able to blow thee home vppon the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine: yet art thou not ſure for to haue it. Nay GOD hath told thee: <hi>Becauſe I haue called, and you refuſed: you ſhall call vppon mee, and I will not</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. 1. 28.</note> 
               <hi>anſwer you.</hi> A dolefull and heauy doome, for a dying man.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Laſtly let vs euer remember, that in time of ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe wee thinke moſt vppon that wee moſt feele: Death beſeegeth vs: Sinn affrighteth vs: our wiues grieueys: our children with-drawe vs: beeing many wayes diſtracted, how ſhall wee then amend? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing then at the weakeſt, how can wee reſiſt Sathan, who is then at the ſtrongeſt? now hee muſt haue vs, or elſe euer looſe vs: nowe therefore ſtandeth the redde Dragon, ready to deuoure his prey. Vaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting him-ſelfe againſt CHRIST IESVS: <hi>I neuer dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for theſe, I neuer was whipped, crucified, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented for them. I neuer promiſed them eternall life, not Paradiſe, not the ioyes of Heauen. And yet loe howe they followe mee vnto their liues ende?</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaunt Sathan: in the Name of CHRIST IESVS. And let all true Chriſtians <hi>Amend ſpeedilie: Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. There is puniſhment threatned,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yee ſhall</hi> all <hi>periſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Amongſt the Philoſophers, to <hi>periſh,</hi> doth vſually
<pb facs="tcp:12983:13"/>
ſignifie, <hi>A returning vnto nothing</hi> which the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of GOD, doe naturally abhorre. For euer ſince that firſt bleſſing <hi>Increaſe and multiplie,</hi> there<note place="margin">Gen. 1.</note> hath beene in the Creatures, a naturall deſire, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue themſelues. In this philoſophicall ſenſe, is not the word here to bee vnderſtood. It were a peece of happineſſe to impenitent perſons, if they might become as though they had neuer beene. But death <hi>ſhall depart from them:</hi> and as the Heart of <hi>Promethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> was (ſay the Poets) alwayes eaten with <hi>Vultures,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo. 9.</note> and not deuoured, ſo ſhall it bee with theſe: They ſhall euer <hi>periſh,</hi> and neuer bee conſumed. In the Scriptures, <hi>To periſh:</hi> is a word of a large extent: contayning in it, the plagues of the Soule, the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment<note place="margin">Pro. 21.</note> of the body, the wrath and curſe of<note place="margin">Dan. 2.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 1.</note> GOD, vpon the Reprobates in this world, and<note place="margin">Ioh. 10. 28.</note> in the world to come euerlaſting condemnation. The meaning then of the word [<hi>periſh</hi>]. Firſt, is this: You ſhall haue in this life the face of GOD againſt you: Heauen ſhal be as Yron, and Earth as Braſſe vnto you. Curſed ſhall you bee in the Citty, curſed in the Fieldes: curſed ſhall you bee in your Barne, curſed in your Store, curſed in the fruites of your Wombes, curſed in the fruites of the Earth, curſed in your heards of Cattle, curſed in your flocks of ſheepe: curſed ſhall be your going out, curſed ſhal be your comming in: your Honours, your Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,<note place="margin">Deu. 28.</note> your Riches, your Children: all the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of GOD ſhall bee turned into curſes, vntill you be deſtroyed and <hi>periſh</hi> vtterly.
<pb facs="tcp:12983:14"/>
This is the portion of the impenitent in this world. Secondly, the meaning of the word (<hi>periſh</hi>) is this: you ſhall in the world to come, bee euerlaſtingly condemned. Which the Schoole-men haue <hi>reduced,</hi> to two <hi>kindes</hi> of torments: <hi>poena damni: paena ſenſus.</hi> 1. the torment of loſſe, or wanting: 2. the torment of ſenſe, and feeling<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the effect of both is this: <hi>you ſhall looſe the ioyes of Heauen, you ſhall feele the paines of hell.</hi> The ioyes of Heauen, are theſe of ſuch valewe, or the loſſe of them ſo great, as ſhould moue vs to <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance?</hi> what thoſe ioyes are, and by conſequence how great their loſſe is, wee may behold as in a Glaſſe darkely: but tongues of men and Angells can in noe wiſe expreſſe. S. <hi>Paul</hi> being rapt into the third<note place="margin">2. Cor. 12.</note> Heauen, heard there ſuch things as cannot bee vtte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Firſt</hi> we may roue at them, by that high <hi>price</hi> which is ſet vpon them. CHRIST the <hi>Sonne,</hi> and <hi>onely Sonne</hi> of GOD, not by <hi>Adoption</hi> but by <hi>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, louing,</hi> and <hi>beſt beloued:</hi> bought them, not with <hi>money,</hi> but with <hi>bloud:</hi> not with the <hi>bloud of Goates</hi> and <hi>Rammes:</hi> but with <hi>his own blood:</hi> not with the <hi>bloud</hi> of <hi>head, handes</hi> or <hi>feete:</hi> but with <hi>his owne heart bloud.</hi> And as hee prayed ſoundly for them him-ſelfe: ſo hath hee prized them vnto his <hi>Friends,</hi> and <hi>Children.</hi> None can enter into them but by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tribulations. They coſt <hi>Paul</hi> a beheadding, <hi>Peter</hi> a<note place="margin">A &amp;. 14. 22</note> crucifiyng: <hi>Steuen</hi> a ſtoning: <hi>millions of Martirs</hi> a racking or burning, a torturing, a tormenting. GOD<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> who is faithfull and true, hath not deceiued his Son, nor ouer-ſold his ioyes vnto his Saints. And therfore
<pb facs="tcp:12983:14"/>
vnſpeakeable are thoſe ioyes, which CHRIST hath purchaſed, and his <hi>Children</hi> obtayned, thorowe a world of miſeries.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly</hi> we may conceiue of them: by taking a <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> view of inferior beauties. Looke vpon the meddows: conſider (ſayth our Sauiour) the Lillies of the field, how they growe and floriſh: I ſay vnto you; that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> in all his glory, was not like to one of theſe: all <hi>Salomons</hi> glory, not like to one Lilly. Hath GOD put ſuch glory and gladneſſe vpon the graſſe of the field? hath hee ſo gorgiouſly attired them? which to day haue a being, but to morrow are cut downe, and caſt into a furnace? how much more then ſhal<note place="margin">Luk. 12. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> be the glory, and ioy of you, O yee of little faith?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly</hi> wee haue a reſemblance of theſe ioyes, in <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> CHRISTS transfiguration: when as his <hi>face</hi> did<note place="margin">Mat. 17.</note> ſhine as the <hi>Sunne,</hi> and his <hi>rayment</hi> was as white as <hi>ſnowe.</hi> For hereby we learne what glory our bodyes ſhall haue in the day of the reſurrection: when (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells vs) <hi>wee ſhall beare the image of the heauenly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 15.</note> and bee like the <hi>Sonne</hi> in glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> the place of bleſſedneſſe, doth informe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> vs of theſe ioyes. <hi>Firſt</hi> it is a place of <hi>puritie and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: no vncleane thing ſhall enter thereinto. Secondly</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apo 21.</note> a place of <hi>beauty,</hi> and <hi>brightneſſe: as cleare as criſtal, gliſtring as Iaſper<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the twelue gates</hi> are <hi>twelue pearles;</hi> the <hi>ſireetes</hi> like gold, and ſhining glaſſe. <hi>Thirdly</hi> a<note place="margin">Apo. 22.</note> place of <hi>roomth,</hi> and <hi>largeneſſe: O Iſrael how great is the houſe of GOD, and how large is the place of his poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Baruch. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> into this <hi>pure, bright, large</hi> place of glorie
<pb facs="tcp:12983:15"/>
ſhall true Conuertes enter: <hi>for where I am<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> (ſaith CHRIST) <hi>there ſhall my ſeruants bee:</hi> and that is<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.</note> not all; but Kingdomes ſhall bee giuen vnto them: <hi>Come yee bleſſed of my Father, poſſeſſe a Kingdome:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2. 29</note> and in this Kingdome, the Lord him-ſelfe will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor<note place="margin">Luk. 12. 37</note> them <hi>with his owne attendants:</hi> and there ſhall they raigne for euermore.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fiftly wee may make coniecture of theſe ioyes, by reflecting our eyes vpon thoſe innumerable perilles, which we haue heere eſcaped. For if ſuch as are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from the daungers of the Sea, do wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully reioyce when they come vnto the ſhore. Much greater then is the ioye of thoſe who hauing beene toſſed in the waues of this World; troubled with ſinnes, with Sathan; with the fraylties of the fleſh, with the feare of hell, (<hi>Quorum periculum probat periuntium multitudo</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregorie</hi>) whoſe dangers appeares by the multitude of thoſe that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh) are nowe arriued at Heauen, for their Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen: and are wholie freed from all their miſeries: <hi>Quanto fuit maius periculum in praelio<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> tanto maius gaudium in triumpho:</hi> (as Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> well ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth:) the more dangers eſcaped, the more ioyes increaſed: as the moſt doubtfull battell, maketh the moſt ioyfull victory.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Laſtly though wee knowe not what it is to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the <hi>Face</hi> of GOD: yet herein conſiſteth the<note place="margin">Exo. 33. 18</note> higheſt degree of happineſſe, and therefore are the ioyes of the Saintes in Heauen ſuper-Superlatiue<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 33. 17.</note> 
               <hi>becauſe their eyes doe alwayes ſee their King in his</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12983:15"/>
               <hi>glorie.</hi> It is a pleaſing ſight and delight-ſome vnto the eye, to behold the Sunne: <hi>Sed illud eſt verum gaudium</hi> (ſaith <hi>S. Bernard</hi>) <hi>non quod ae creatura ſed quod de creatore concipitur:</hi> but that is the true and onely ioy indeede, which is conceiued from the <hi>Creator,</hi> not from the <hi>Creature. Iohn</hi> leapt in his Mothers wombe, when but the Mother of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker came neere vnto him: the Wiſe-men reioyced exceedingly, when they but ſawe his Starre. The <hi>Bethſhemits</hi> were comforted at the ſight of his Ark, were theſe cauſes of <hi>great</hi> and <hi>vnwonted</hi> gladneſſe? Then are the Saints <hi>rauiſhed</hi> with ioy in Heauen, who behold theyr <hi>Creator</hi> face to face. If the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhouted for ioy, ſo as the earth did ring againe with the ſound of their noyſe when <hi>Salomon</hi> was<note place="margin">1. King. 1.</note> proclaimed King: O what a <hi>Hallaluiah</hi> is there in Heauen, at the ſight of the King of Peace, crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in his Throne of Glorie? <hi>Huic comparata, om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis aliunde iucunàitas, maeror eſt: omnis ſuauitas, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lor: omne dulce, amarum: omne decorum, foedum.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Saint Bernard</hi>) In compariſon of this, <hi>all ioy,</hi> is <hi>ſadneſſe:</hi> all <hi>ſweetneſſe, ſowerneſse:</hi> all <hi>beauty, black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe:</hi> yea <hi>all</hi> the delights in the World put them together; which haue beene, which are, which ſhall bee to the day of Iudgement: <hi>all,</hi> are but as a <hi>droppe</hi> of water, to the mayne <hi>Ocean,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of that bleſſedneſſe which wee ſhall drinke from the euer liuing fountaine of the face of GOD. For if wee finde ſuch ſtore of ſweetneſſe in a peece of <hi>one little Creature</hi> (bee it Sugar, or Honie; or
<pb facs="tcp:12983:16"/>
ſuch like:) what ſhall wee not finde in the <hi>Creator?</hi> if the foote-ſteppes of the goodneſſe of GOD a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound in pleaſures: what hath not the <hi>fountaine</hi> of goodneſſe, GOD himſelfe? The conſideration whereof cauſed <hi>Moyſes</hi> to ſue vnto GOD, that hee might ſee his glory. Compelled <hi>Dauid</hi> oftentimes humbly to requeſt, that hee might behold the face<note place="margin">Pſa. 27. 8.</note> of his GOD, and when GOD ſaid vnto him:<note place="margin">Pſa. 80.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeke my face:</hi> his heart anſwered as an Eccho, <hi>O Lord I will ſeeke thy face.</hi> And as a man not contented hee treble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h his requeſt. <hi>O thou ſhepheard of Iſrael, cauſe thy face to ſhine vpon mee, that I may bee ſaued.</hi> Twice more hee prayeth. <hi>O thou ſhepheard of Iſrael &amp;c.</hi> His ſaluation and eternall happineſſe, hee repoſeth in the <hi>ſight</hi> of GOD: for hee knewe full well, that <hi>in his preſence, there was fulnes of ioy for euermore.</hi> Let mee<note place="margin">Pſa. 16. 11.</note> but ſhewe you now, what Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh of the ioyes of Heauen, and ſo will I paſſe vnto that which followeth. <q>Wee may (ſaith hee) ſooner tell you, what they are not; then what they are. Yet take a ſurusie of thoſe manifolde benefits, which GOD beſtoweth vpon our baſe, and ignoble bodies. Shed out both vpon good and badde, from the Heauens, from the Ayre, from the Earth, from the Waters, from light, from darkeneſſe, from heate, from cold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, from all the creatures, ſhed alſo out, by ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, to exclude a loathing. Doth GOD beſtow vpon our bodies, and promiſcuaily vppon all; theſe excellent benefits? Then O Lord howe great and wonderfull are thoſe good things which thou haſt
<pb facs="tcp:12983:16"/>
laid vp for thine Elect in the Kingdome of Heauen? if theſe be ſo good, which thou haſt giuen to good and badde: what ſhall they bee, which thou haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued onely for the good? if they bee ſoe pleaſant, which thou ſendeſt to friendes, and enemies: howe ſweete are thoſe, which thy friends ſhall enioy? if there bee ſo many comfortes in the valley of teares: what ſhall there bee in the day of marriage? if thou beeſt ſo kind vnto vs, in this priſon of ours: how wilt thon imbrace and hugge vs, when we come into thy Kingdome?</q> Into that <hi>euerlaſting</hi> Kingdome, where <hi>euerlaſting</hi> glory ſhall bee vpon our heads: where that which we <hi>would haue,</hi> ſhal be preſent with vs: and that we <hi>would not haue,</hi> ſhal be as ſent from vs: where there ſhal be a meaſure of ioy, <hi>heaped vp, ſhaken together, preſſed downe, running ouer; menſura ſine menſura</hi> (as <hi>Bernard</hi> ſpeaketh) a meaſure without meaſure. Where we ſhall haue <hi>health</hi> without ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: <hi>ſtrength</hi> without weakeneſſe. <hi>freedome,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bondage: <hi>beautie</hi> without blackneſſe: <hi>Knowledge</hi> without ignorance, plenty without want: <hi>peace</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out trouble: <hi>ſafety</hi> without feare: <hi>life</hi> without death: <hi>glory</hi> without ſhame. Where wee ſhall be <hi>filled</hi> with ioy: yet beeing <hi>filled</hi> wee ſhall ſtill <hi>deſire,</hi> leaſt our <hi>fulneſse</hi> procure a loathing: and in <hi>deſiring</hi> wee ſhall alwayes bee <hi>filled,</hi> leaſt our <hi>deſire</hi> beget a <hi>greeuing:</hi> (to conclude) neither eye hath ſeene, nor eare hath heard, nor heart of man can conceiue thoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent things that are prepared for vs. Neyther can GOD giue more: nor man receiue more then we
<pb facs="tcp:12983:17"/>
ſhall there inioy. And is not this then a moſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable loſſe, to bee debarred from theſe ioves of Heauen? Mee thinkes the remembrance of it ſhould diſmaye the heart of a wicked man. When hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counteth with himſelfe that hee ſhall bee ſhutte out off doores with <hi>Dogges,</hi> that hee ſhallbe excluded from thoſe <hi>vnſpeakable ioyes,</hi> which CHRIST IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS hath bought with his pretious heart bloud: that hee ſhall bee bereft of that <hi>glory,</hi> whereof the beauty of the moſt glorious Creatures is but a ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſhadow: that hee ſhall be caſt out from that <hi>pure, bright,</hi> and <hi>large</hi> place of happineſſe: from an <hi>Eternall Kingdome.</hi> Did the loſſe of the Arke of<note place="margin">1. Sam. 4.</note> GOD cauſe <hi>Elye</hi> to breake his neck? This then is inough to breake a <hi>Pharaohs</hi> heart in peeces; to know that after <hi>troubles</hi> heere, there is no hope of <hi>har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour,</hi> of <hi>reſt,</hi> of <hi>ſafty</hi> in the world to come: that he ſhal be depryued of the <hi>face</hi> of GOD, the <hi>ſight</hi> of CHRIST, the <hi>fellowſhip</hi> of the Spirit, the <hi>compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> of holy Angells, and bleſſed Saintes: finally that hee ſhall haue no part in that <hi>great meaſure</hi> of ioy; which is ſo infinite as it cannot enter into vs, but wee muſt enter into it: <hi>Thou good and faithfull</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 25. 21</note> 
               <hi>ſeruant enter into thy Maiſters ioy.</hi> O wofull, and vnſufferable loſſe! more then can bee counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nayled by the gayning of ten thouſand Worldes: Nay all the teares which ſhall be in Hell: will (ſaith <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi>) neuer be ſufficient, to <hi>bewayle</hi> the loſſe of Heauen.</p>
            <p>And is this all the puniſhment, the impenitent
<pb facs="tcp:12983:17"/>
ſhall ſuſtaine? ſhall they onely looſe the ioyes of Heauen? we may not ſtay heere: <hi>They ſhal pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh,</hi> they ſhall likewiſe feele the terrible <hi>paines of Hell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many motiues are there (ſaith <hi>Saint Hierom</hi>) to ſtirre vs vp to amendment of our liues. The conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the <hi>teares,</hi> and of the <hi>bloud,</hi> which CHRIST ſhedde for ſinners: our owne ennume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>offences;</hi> the <hi>weakneſſe</hi> of <hi>our</hi> bodies, and <hi>frailty</hi> of our liues: GODS continued mercy to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes vs: his <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>reuenging power:</hi> but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the feare of looſing the <hi>ioyes of Heauen.</hi> All theſe are as ſpurres to prick vs forward to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: and as Trumpets to rowſe vs vp from our carnall ſecuritye. Yet ſuch is the dulneſſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and ſo dead a ſleepe are ſome in their ſinnes, as ſuch motiues as theſe will worke but ſmall effect in them. Let CHRIST <hi>weepe</hi> till his Head, and Heart ake: let him ſuffer neuer ſo extreame <hi>Torments:</hi> let ſinnes bee as redde as ſcarlet: and <hi>liues</hi> of all thinges moſt vncertaine: ſhewe GODS <hi>mercies,</hi> tell of his <hi>iudgments,</hi> Preach of the loſſe of Heauen. Yet were there no <hi>Hell</hi> to receiue them; or <hi>Tortures</hi> prouided for them: they would eaſily put off all theſe with a <hi>Tuſh:</hi> and bee as reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute for their owne deſtruction as <hi>Heſter</hi> was for the ſauing of her people, <hi>If wee periſh, wee pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh. Oderunt peccare mali formi dine paenae.</hi> Wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked<note place="margin">Heſt. 4. 16.</note> ones, muſt bee ſcarred from ſinne, with feare
<pb facs="tcp:12983:18"/>
of puniſhments: let them then ſet before their eyes the fearefull and horrible paines of heil.</p>
            <p>Theſe in the Scriptures, are expreſſed by diuers<note place="margin">Apoc. 10.</note> names, <hi>Sometimes</hi> they are called <hi>fire<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> hee that is not written in the booke of life: is ſent into a lake of fire.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. <hi>66.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>Sometimes</hi> they are tearmed <hi>a Worme: their worme ſhall not die. Verme roditur conſcientia, igne cremantur corpora:</hi> (ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>) with the worme is their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences gnawed, and with the fire are their bodies burned. Sometimes againe, are they ſet out, by the loathſome ſtench of <hi>Brimſtone: vppon the wicked hee</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 11. 6.</note> 
               <hi>will raine fire and brimſtone.</hi> Otherwhiles by <hi>weeping,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13. 42</note> and <hi>gnaſhing of teeth. Weeping</hi> becauſe of the <hi>fire</hi> that will not be quenched: and gnaſhing, becauſe of the <hi>worme</hi> that wil not bee <hi>killed.</hi> the <hi>one</hi> comming from<note place="margin">Eſa. 65. 13. 14.</note> 
               <hi>griefe,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> from <hi>rage. Sometimes</hi> they beare the names of <hi>thirſt,</hi> of <hi>hunger,</hi> of <hi>ſorrow,</hi> of <hi>ſhame.</hi> And ſuch penury is there in hell, as there is nothing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecue the damned which are therein. The rich man begged a droppe of water, and could not haue it. <hi>guttam petijt</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) <hi>qui micam negauit:</hi> hee craued a droppe, that denied a crumme. Neyther is it a little torment to bee impriſoned, and tortured by the <hi>vgglie Fiendes</hi> of hell: by thoſe Etheopian An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelles; (as <hi>Cyrill</hi> calleth them) whoſe armes (ſaith <hi>Caſsian</hi>) are like the heades of Dragons, whoſe <hi>eyes</hi> ſhoote forth arrowes of fire: whoſe <hi>teeth,</hi> are like the teeth of Elephants; whoſe <hi>tayles</hi> are like the tayles of Scorpions, that is <hi>guſhfull,</hi> and <hi>griſly Diuils:</hi> if the ſight of <hi>one</hi> of them be able to bereaue a man
<pb facs="tcp:12983:18"/>
of his wittes: O how great will the horrour be, when they ſhall <hi>all</hi> appeare? And what doth the <hi>place</hi> of puniſhment afford? that place of <hi>confuſion?</hi> of <hi>dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</hi> of <hi>chaines?</hi> of <hi>moſt horrible ſhapes?</hi> but euen<note place="margin">Math. 22.</note> Ecchoes of woes. Well then; ſuppoſe one to be <hi>bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> in a lake of fire, hauing a <hi>Viper</hi> at his heart, alwayes <hi>gnawing</hi> and <hi>ſtinging his ſoule:</hi> imagine boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>brimſtone</hi> to bee powred vppon him; that with the <hi>heat</hi> thereof, hee is ſcalded: with the <hi>ſmoake</hi> thereof, hee is ſtifled, and with the <hi>noyſome ſauour</hi> continually choaked: let him <hi>weepe, wayle, wring</hi> his handes, and ſtand <hi>gnaſhing</hi> of his teeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> let him be euer <hi>languiſhing</hi> and <hi>pining</hi> with want of foode, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nay him all things which may any waie eaſe him. Conceiue yet further that he is <hi>bound</hi> handes and feete; that he is <hi>affrighted</hi> and <hi>tormented</hi> with <hi>vgglie Diuells,</hi> and compaſſed round about with <hi>horrible darkeneſſe.</hi> Thinke well of the miſery of ſuch a man: and know that theſe are the paynes of an impenitent wretch in hell. Theſe the paynes? nay (<hi>my beloued</hi>) theſe are not the tenth part of Hels torments. CHRIST calleth them <hi>Euerlaſting paynes</hi>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> As they are <hi>extream</hi> without <hi>decreaſing,</hi> ſo are they <hi>endleſse</hi> without all <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 25.</note> There are <hi>ſighes,</hi> with-out pittying: <hi>cries</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verl. laſt.</note> without moning: <hi>lamentation,</hi> with-out relecuing: <hi>a flood of black flimes, euer flowing: ibi dolores tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent animas, non extorquent, puniunt corpora, non fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niunt:</hi> (as <hi>Proſper</hi> ſpeaketh) there is a <hi>Death,</hi> which alwayes liueth, and a <hi>Life,</hi> which alwayes dyeth:
<pb facs="tcp:12983:19"/>
there hee that <hi>tortoreth,</hi> fainteth not, and hee that <hi>ſuffereth</hi> fayleth not: There is <hi>Euer</hi> parching fire, for warming loue: <hi>Euer</hi> baniſhment, for reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: <hi>Euer</hi> heauineſſe, for ſinging; <hi>Euer</hi> darkneſſe for ſhining: <hi>Euer</hi> fetters, for crownes; <hi>Euer</hi> gna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of teeth, for clapping of handes: <hi>Euer</hi> miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable immortality and immortall miſerve. Alaſſe <hi>who is able</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eſay</hi>) <hi>to dwell in euerlaſting bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 33. 14.</note> It were ſome comfort in the middeſt of afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to thinke that <hi>one day,</hi> they will come vnto an end; and the damned ſpirits in hell, had they but a <hi>little hope,</hi> that after the ſpace of manye <hi>thouſand, thouſand yeares</hi> they ſhould bee releaſed: this <hi>little ſparke</hi> in the middeſt of their flames, would in ſome ſort make them ioyfull: but <hi>Euer</hi> to burne, <hi>Euer</hi> to boyle, <hi>Euer</hi> to weepe, <hi>Euer</hi> to wring, <hi>Euer</hi> to bee in chaynes, to ſuffer vnſufferable torments. <hi>Euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting paynes?</hi> This is that which cutteth heart-ſtrings a ſunder. Yet is not this all. For as they are <hi>eternall</hi> with-out <hi>redemption:</hi> ſo are they <hi>Generall</hi> with-out <hi>exception.</hi> For <hi>firſt; all</hi> ſuffer them: and iudge you,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> what a dolefull ſight it will bee, to ſee infinite mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of males and females, continually without any intermiſſion, <hi>hacking</hi> and <hi>hewing,</hi> their teeth toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: to heare howling and crying, <hi>Woe, woe, be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs, that euer wee were borne:</hi> to heare one Diuel, one damned Ghoſt, calling vnto another, to <hi>ſtrike, to rend,</hi> to <hi>kill,</hi> to <hi>ſpoyle,</hi> to <hi>heape on coales,</hi> to <hi>poure on Brimſtone:</hi> like one that is preſſing to death, who cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb facs="tcp:12983:19"/>
for more waights to bee caſt vpon him. <hi>Secondly</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> as they <hi>all</hi> ſuffer in <hi>all</hi> parts, in <hi>all</hi> the members of their <hi>bodies,</hi> in <hi>all</hi> the powers of their <hi>ſoules.</hi> they haue <hi>corporall</hi> flames with-out, and <hi>ſpirituall</hi> flames with-in: no part; no power is free. Haſt thou offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with thy <hi>Head?</hi> thou ſhalt haue <hi>ſcalding:</hi> haſt thou offended with thine <hi>Eyes?</hi> thou ſhalt haue <hi>wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping:</hi> haſt thou offended with thy <hi>Mouth?</hi> thou ſhalt haue <hi>howling:</hi> with thy <hi>Tongue?</hi> thou ſhalt haue <hi>ſcorching:</hi> with thine <hi>Eares?</hi> thou ſhalt haue <hi>yelling:</hi> with thy <hi>Noſe?</hi> thou ſhalt haue <hi>ſtincking:</hi> with thy <hi>Feete?</hi> thou ſhalt haue <hi>fettering:</hi> with thy <hi>Handes?</hi> thou ſhalt haue <hi>wringing:</hi> with thy <hi>Heart?</hi> thou ſhalt haue <hi>gnawing;</hi> in thy <hi>Soule,</hi> and <hi>Body, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> and <hi>boyling. Pro diſparibus generibus peccatorum ſunt diſparia tormenta ſuppliciorum</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>) <hi>euery man ſhall receiue according to his ſeuerall</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.</note> 
               <hi>workes.</hi> Coniecture yet further of <hi>Hells tortures,</hi> by things of no accompt. Put thy foote into a ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing bath, and how doſt thou grieue? what ſorrow doſt thou conceiue? if thou beeſt vexed with a ſharp burning ague; how doſt thou toſſe, and tumble, and art out of quiet? is the <hi>ſcalding</hi> of thy foote, or a <hi>fit</hi> of an Ague ſo grieuous vnto fleſh and bloud? which are but <hi>Flea-bitings,</hi> no though thou did deſt abide them, thy whole life long? O howe then wilt thou bee able to endure <hi>euerlaſting burnings?</hi> Will CHRIST <hi>now</hi> profit thee, who ſtretched his armes out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the Croſſe for ſinners? No, hee will <hi>now</hi> 
               <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12983:20"/>
            <p>NOW IESVS CHRIST our Lord, and GOD, Euen the Father which hath loued vs, and giuen vs euerlaſting conſolation by his ſpirit: and good hope through grace: purge our dead con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, and ſtabliſh our hearts in euery good word and worke vnto the end<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that beeing made the ſeruants of GOD, wee may haue our fruit in holineſſe, and in the end eternall life. Amen.</p>
            <closer>Laus DEO.</closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12983:20"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
